<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="section_e-ef-series">
    <title>Description of E-Series and EF-Series Systems</title>
    <para>
        The family of E-series and EF-series systems provides performance-efficient, high-density block storage aimed primarily at application-driven workloads.
    </para>
    <para>
        NetApp E-Series systems are designed to provide:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            Simple, low-touch administration
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            Flexible, reliable SAN storage
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            Extreme capacity and density
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            High performance GB/s or IOPS
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            Performance, power, and space efficiency
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            Consistent, low latency
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            Consistently high IOPS and throughput
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            Enterprise-class capabilities (reliability, availability, manageability)
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
        The NetApp EF-Series is an all-flash storage array that brings together extreme performance and enterprise-grade reliability to create a system optimized for latency-sensitive workloads.  Building on a heritage of performance leadership, its core architecture has been proven in the world’s most demanding and complex computing environments.  Its field-proven design is the culmination of 20-years of industry knowledge focused on designing enterprise-class storage.  Leveraging experience from over 650,000 systems shipped, the fully-redundant EF-Series all-flash array is architected to provide the highest levels of reliability, availability and data protection.
    </para>
    <para>
        The E and EF-Series run on the enterprise-proven <trademark class="registered">SANtricity</trademark> software platform. SANtricity is designed to combine sustainable, low-latency performance with enterprise-class availability and protection.  Its streamlined firmware is well-suited for the extreme demands of latency-sensitive workloads. And SANtricity helps keep I/O flowing with automated path failover, online administration, advanced data protection, proactive monitoring and repair, non-disruptive upgrades, and extensive diagnostic capabilities.
    </para>
    <para>
        E-series’ Dynamic Disk Pools (DDP) provide an alternative to standard RAID groups. They simplify protection by removing the complexity of configuring RAID groups and allocating hot spares. Utilization is improved by dynamically spreading data, parity, and spare capacity across all drives in a pool, reducing performance bottlenecks due to hot-spots. Additionally, should a drive failure occur, DDP enables return to optimal state significantly faster than RAID6, while reducing the performance impact during the reconstruction of a failed drive. DDP also offers greater protection from multiple drive failures by prioritizing the reconstruction of the most critical segments.
    </para>
</section>
