<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<appendix xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="5.0" xml:id="appendix_packaging">
    <title>Packaging</title>
    <section xml:id="appendix.packaging.requirements">
        <title>Packaging and Downloading Requirements</title>
        <para>
            Refer to the following link for packaging and downloading requirements: <link xlink:href="http://wiki.openstack.org/Getopenstack"/>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="appendix.packaging.install">
        <title>Installation and Uninstallation</title>
        <para>
            Refer to the following link for install/uninstall-related information: <link xlink:href="http://wiki.openstack.org/Getopenstack"/>
        </para>
        <para>
            Refer to the following link for documentation on the E-Series SANtricity software: <link xlink:href="http://support.netapp.com/documentation/productlibrary/index.html?productID=61197"/>
        </para>
        <para>
            Refer to the following link for documentation on configuring dm-multipath on Linux: <link xlink:href="https://library.netapp.com/ecmdocs/ECMP1217221/html/GUID-34FA2578-0A83-4ED3-B4B3-8401703D65A6.html"/>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="appendix.packaging.upgrading">
        <title>Upgrading and Reverting</title>
        <para>
            Refer to the following link for upgrading/reverting-related information: <link xlink:href="http://wiki.openstack.org/Getopenstack"/>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="appendix.packaging.licensing">
        <title>Licensing</title>
        <para>
            OpenStack is released under the Apache 2.0 license.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="appendix.packaging.versioning">
        <title>Versioning</title>
        <para>
            Presently, there is no separate versioning system for NetApp’s Cinder drivers, but are instead distinguished by the enclosing OpenStack release’s versioning and release system.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="appendix.packaging.deprecation">
        <title>Deprecated Drivers</title>
        <para>
            In the OpenStack Havana release, NetApp deprecated a variety of management-integrated drivers that had been available in previous OpenStack releases. The driver names include:
            <programlisting>
cinder.volume.drivers.netapp.iscsi.NetAppCmodeISCSIDriver
cinder.volume.drivers.netapp.nfs.NetAppCmodeNfsDriver
cinder.volume.drivers.netapp.iscsi.NetAppISCSIDriver
cinder.volume.drivers.netapp.nfs.NetAppNfsDriver
            </programlisting>
            The direct (and now unified) driver available in the Havana release provides equivalent functionality to these drivers for the various OpenStack services, but without the complex configuration and requirements to operate additional management software and infrastructure. 
        </para>
        <para>
            In situations where it is necessary to leverage the management-integrated drivers in a Havana-based OpenStack deployment, NetApp has ported the drivers to the Havana code base and made them available for download from a separate git repository located at <link xlink:href="https://github.com/NetApp/cinder/tree/stable/havana"/>. 
        </para>
    </section>
</appendix>
