<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<appendix xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="5.0" xml:id="appendix_debug">
    <title>Troubleshooting</title>
    <section xml:id="appendix.debug.common_problems">
        <title>Common Problems</title>
        <para>
            Common problems listed below are followed by the <command>cinder</command> or <command>nova</command> CLI command and possible reasons for the occurrence of the problem.
            <!-- rdc: the titles here are explicitly numbered vs autonumbered due to docbook error when overflowing implicit table when number of item exceeds 9 -->
            <formalpara>
                <title>1. Create volume operation fails with an error status</title>
                    <programlisting>
cinder create <replaceable>size_gb</replaceable>
                    </programlisting>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>No space left on the NetApp volume or NetApp volume does not have sufficient free space to host the specified OpenStack volume. Here NetApp volume refers to a FlexVol volume inside the configured Storage Virtual Machine (SVM aka Vserver) for Clustered Data ONTAP driver. It refers to NetApp volume names configured in Cinder as parameter <option>netapp_volume_list</option> or NetApp volumes in the configured vFiler unit as parameter <option>netapp_vfiler</option> or system wide NetApp volumes for 7-mode storage system.</listitem>
                        <listitem>Cinder API service is down.</listitem>
                        <listitem>Cinder scheduler service is down.</listitem>
                        <listitem>Cinder scheduler reports sufficient available space on NetApp backend but Cinder volume fails to create backend:
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>The Grizzly-based iSCSI driver for Clustered Data ONTAP and 7-mode driver report available space as infinite and hence failure may occur when no NetApp volume can host the OpenStack volume.</listitem>
                                <listitem>The Grizzly-based NFS driver Clustered Data ONTAP and 7-mode report available space as the sum of available space of all configured NFS exports and hence failure may occur when no single NetApp volume can host the OpenStack volume of the given size.</listitem>
                                <listitem>The Havana-based iSCSI and NFS driver for Clustered Data ONTAP report the available capacity for largest NetApp volume in the configured Storage Virtual Machine (SVM aka Vserver). Capacity mismatch might fail volume creation.</listitem>
                                <listitem>The Havana-based iSCSI and NFS driver for 7-mode storage system report the available capacity as sum of available space of all configured NetApp volumes and hence failure may occur when no single NetApp volume can host the OpenStack volume of the given size.</listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>The Havana based NFS driver for Clustered Data ONTAP has the configuration option <option>netapp_vserver</option> to specify the Storage Virtual Machine (SVM aka Vserver) to use for provisioning. It may so happen that the NFS exports specified in the configuration and the NetApp volumes in the SVM do not coincide.</listitem>
                        <listitem>NFS service is not running on the NetApp storage server in case of NFS drivers.</listitem>
                        <listitem>NFS mount for exports failed on the Cinder node due to incorrect export policy or insufficient privileges in case of NFS drivers.</listitem>
                        <listitem>NetApp volumes getting full because snapshots occupying storage space.</listitem>
                        <listitem>NetApp volumes are shared between OpenStack Cinder and other client side applications.</listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>2. Create volume with volume-type operation fails with error status</title>
                    <programlisting>
cinder create --volume-type <replaceable>volume_type</replaceable> <replaceable>size_gb</replaceable>
                    </programlisting>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>All the reasons mentioned under Item 1 in this appendix.</listitem>
                        <listitem>The NetApp backend(s) with available space do not support at least one of the extra-specs bound to the volume-type requested. Hence, it does not return the extra spec in volume stats call to the Cinder scheduler.</listitem>
                        <listitem>In Clustered Data ONTAP drivers operation fails due to:
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>No NetApp volume supports all extra specs bound to the volume-type.</listitem>
                                <listitem>The configured storage admin user does not have sufficient privileges to query specific storage service catalog features required to support the volume-type configuration.</listitem>
                                <listitem>The configured IP address/host name is on a SVM network interface but the volume-type support requires cluster wide API access.</listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>3. Create volume from image-id operation fails with an error status</title>
                    <programlisting>
cinder create --image-id <replaceable>image-id</replaceable> <replaceable>size_gb</replaceable>
                    </programlisting>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>All the reasons mentioned under Item 1 in this appendix.</listitem>
                        <listitem>The Grizzly-based NFS driver does not have the mentioned operation supported. It may be required to use the latest code from the NetApp git repository, from the <literal>stable/grizzly</literal> branch in order to get a supported version.</listitem>
                        <listitem>Glance related services are down.</listitem>
                        <listitem>The image could not be downloaded from glance because of download error.</listitem>
                        <listitem>Havana-based NFS drivers may experience a shortage in storage capacity due to space occupied by image cache files. Image cache files are files with prefix img-cache, and are periodically cleaned by the driver.</listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>4. Create volume from image-id with volume-type operation fails with an error status</title>
                    <programlisting>
cinder create --image-id <replaceable>image-id</replaceable> --volume-type <replaceable>volume_type</replaceable> <replaceable>size_gb</replaceable>
                    </programlisting>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>All the reasons mentioned under Items 1, 2, and 3 in this appendix.</listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>5. Create snapshot operation fails with an error status</title>
                    <programlisting>
cinder snapshot-create <replaceable>volume-id</replaceable>
                    </programlisting>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>The FlexClone license is not installed.</listitem>
                        <listitem>The NetApp volume hosting the source OpenStack volume does not have sufficient available space.</listitem>
                        <listitem>Any maintenance operation by a storage admin directly at the storage backend causing LUN or file unavailability.</listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>6. Create volume from snapshot operation fails with an error status</title>
                    <programlisting>
cinder create --snapshot-id <replaceable>snapshot-id</replaceable> <replaceable>size_gb</replaceable>
                    </programlisting>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>All reason mentioned under Items 1 &amp; 5 in this appendix.</listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>7. Create cloned volume operation fails with an error status</title>
                    <programlisting>
cinder create --source-volid <replaceable>volume-id</replaceable> <replaceable>size_gb</replaceable>
                    </programlisting>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>All reason mentioned under Items 1 &amp; 5 in this appendix.</listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>8. Volume attach operation in nova fails</title>
                    <programlisting>
nova volume-attach <replaceable>instance-id</replaceable> <replaceable>volume-id</replaceable> <replaceable>path</replaceable> <replaceable>size_gb</replaceable>
                    </programlisting>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>iSCSI drivers:
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>The iSCSI license may not be installed.</listitem>
                                <listitem>The iSCSI service on the <command>nova-compute</command> host may not be running.</listitem>
                                <listitem>The iSCSI portal can not be found. No network interface of type iSCSI has been created.</listitem>
                                <listitem>The network is not reachable due to firewall, configuration, or transient issues.</listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>9. Volume extend operation fails for Havana based drivers</title>
                    <programlisting>
cinder extend <replaceable>volume-id</replaceable> <replaceable>new_size_gb</replaceable> <replaceable>size_gb</replaceable>
                    </programlisting>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>The NetApp volume hosting the OpenStack volume has insufficient space.</listitem>
                        <listitem>iSCSI drivers
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>Reason mentioned under Item 5 in this appendix.</listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>NFS drivers
                            <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>The disk image format of the Cinder volume is not <literal>raw</literal> or <literal>qcow2</literal>.</listitem>
                            </itemizedlist>
                        </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>10. Volume upload to image operation fails</title>
                    <programlisting>
cinder upload-to-image <replaceable>volume-id</replaceable> <replaceable>image</replaceable> <replaceable>size_gb</replaceable>
                    </programlisting>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>The Glance service is down.</listitem>
                        <listitem>All reasons mentioned under Item 8 in this appendix.</listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>11. Volume backup and restore operation fails</title>
                    <programlisting>
cinder backup-create <replaceable>volume-id</replaceable> <replaceable>size_gb</replaceable>
cinder backup-restore <replaceable>volume-id</replaceable> <replaceable>size_gb</replaceable>
                    </programlisting>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>The Cinder backup service is not running.</listitem>
                        <listitem>All reasons mentioned under Item 8 in this appendix.</listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>12. Volume migration operation fails</title>
                    <programlisting>
cinder migrate <replaceable>volume-id</replaceable> <replaceable>host</replaceable>
                    </programlisting>
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>All reasons mentioned under Item 8 in this appendix.</listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
            </formalpara>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="appendix.debug.triage">
        <title>Triage and Data Collection</title>
        <para>
            Please use the NetApp OpenStack Communities site to track or report issues related to Cinder. In case of issues, the data can be collected from logs printed by each of the below mentioned process. Logs need to be collected for Cinder related processes. For Glance and Nova verifying the service up status is sufficient.
        </para>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Cinder processes</title>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>cinder-api</listitem>
                <listitem>cinder-scheduler</listitem>
                <listitem>cinder-volume</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Nova processes</title>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>nova-api</listitem>
                <listitem>nova-scheduler</listitem>
                <listitem>nova-cpu</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Glance processes</title>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>glance-api</listitem>
                <listitem>glance-registry</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </simplesect>
        <simplesect>
            <title>Swift processes</title>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>swift-object-server</listitem>
                <listitem>swift-object-replicator</listitem>
                <listitem>swift-object-updator</listitem>
                <listitem>swift-object-auditor</listitem>
                <listitem>swift-container-server</listitem>
                <listitem>swift-container-replicator</listitem>
                <listitem>swift-container-updator</listitem>
                <listitem>swift-container-auditor</listitem>
                <listitem>swift-account-server</listitem>
                <listitem>swift-account-replicator</listitem>
                <listitem>swift-account-auditor</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </simplesect>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="appendix.debug.references">
        <title>References</title>
        <para>
            The following references were used in this paper:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>NIST Cloud Definition <link xlink:href="http://www.nist.gov"/></listitem>
                <listitem>OpenStack Foundation <link xlink:href="http://www.openstack.org"/></listitem>
                <listitem>Cloud Data Management Interface (CDMI) <link xlink:href="http://www.snia.org/cdmi"/></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            For additional information, visit:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>For more information on the operation, deployment of, or support for NetApp’s OpenStack integrations: 
                    <link xlink:href="http://communities.netapp.com/groups/openstack"/></listitem>
                <listitem>For source code for OpenStack, including NetApp contributions, available through Github: <link xlink:href="http://www.github.com/openstack"/></listitem>
                <listitem>For more information about NetApp’s participation in OpenStack, visit the NetApp Community site: 
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.netapp.com/openstack"/></listitem>
                <listitem>For more information about OpenStack history: <link xlink:href="http://www.openstack.org"/> or <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OpenStack"/></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="appendix.debug.support">
        <title>Support</title>
        <para>
            Community support is available through the NetApp Communities site: <link xlink:href="http://communities.netapp.com/groups/openstack"/>.
        </para>
        <para>
            NetApp’s Interoperability Matrix (IMT) details components and versions of qualified configurations.  Since the majority of OpenStack provides a control plane it’s not presently explicitly called out, but host operating system, hypervisor, and other components involved in the data path should be noted.  
        </para>
        <para>
            <link xlink:href="http://support.netapp.com/matrix/"/>
        </para>
        <para>
            The NetApp OpenStack team presently intends to provide maintenance of the two most recently released versions of OpenStack. For example, during Juno development, all code that is part of the Havana and Icehouse official branches are supported. Upon Juno release, direct maintenance for Havana would be dropped and maintenance for Icehouse is added.
        </para>
        <para>
            NetApp can provide customized support options for production requirements. For more information, please contact your sales team.
        </para>
    </section>
</appendix>
